<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The birth, purpose, and mortall vvound of the Romish holie League Describing in a mappe the enuie of Sathans shauelings, and the follie of their wisedome, through the Almighties prouidence. By I.L.</title>
            <author>I. L., fl. 1589.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1589</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 23 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04964</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15106</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106736</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842447</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842447</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7100</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04964)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7100)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 473:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The birth, purpose, and mortall vvound of the Romish holie League Describing in a mappe the enuie of Sathans shauelings, and the follie of their wisedome, through the Almighties prouidence. By I.L.</title>
                  <author>I. L., fl. 1589.</author>
                  <author>Lea, James, fl. 1589, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By T. Orwin] for Thomas Cadman,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1589.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Sometimes attributed to James Lea.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Verse and prose.</note>
                  <note>The "mortal wound" was the defeat of the Spanish Armada.--Folger Shakespeare Library Catalog.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Holy League, 1576-1593 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7100:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7100:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Birth, Purpoſe, and mortall VVound of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh holie League.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Deſcribing in a Mappe the enuie of Sathans Shaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, and the follie of their wiſedome, through the Almighties proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By I. L.</p>
            <bibl>
               <hi>Pſalm. 2. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ. 2. &amp; 4.</hi>
            </bibl>
            <q>The Kings of the earth band themſelues, and the Princes came together againſt the Lord, and and againſt his Anointed.
But hee that dwelleth in Heauen ſhall laugh: the Lord ſhall haue them in deriſion.</q>
            <p>Imprinted at London for <hi>Thomas Cadman.</hi> 1589.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:7100:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7100:2"/>
            <head>The Birth, Purpoſe, and mortall VVound of the Romiſh Holie League.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Antichriſtian intruſion into the Empire, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing manifeſted the Pope to be that man of ſinn whereof S. <hi>Paule</hi> ſpeaketh to the <hi>Theſſalonians;</hi> and the innumerable deceiuing fantaſies, tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and vaine inuentions, wherewith the erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath made dronke the Nations of the earth, diſcouering her to bee that purple Whore ſitting on the Beaſt with ſeauen heads, or rather (as the Angell interpreteth in the Reuelation) on the Citie with ſeauen hills: hath (through the mightie working of Gods ſpirit by his zealous Miniſters) ſo laid open the ſkirts of their filthines, that the moſt part of Chriſtian Princes with their people haue imbraced the free libertie of the Goſpel, and freed themſelues from her An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian yoake. Whereupon Sathan (chiefe Patrone of that Regiment) ſeeing the decaie of his Empire, the diſcredite of his Vice-gerent, and the open defamation of his infamous Spouſe (the Romiſh Church); thought it high time to ſet too his helping hand, the rather for that his kingdome draweth ſo neere an ende. Therefore in the ſilentſt time of night (a fit houre for the Prince of darkneſſe to take in hand a helliſh enterpriſe) he poſted to his terreſtriall Pallace at <hi>Rome;</hi> where ſeating himſelfe in the ſecret chamber of his Papall Vicar, heethus began: The care (right truſtie and welbeloued) of infinite thy predeceſſors, together with thy approued diligence for the ſuppreſsing of Chriſtian ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, (the onelie obſtacle and hindrance of my happineſſe) is to me no leſſe knowen, than graciouſlie accepted: but thou ſeeſt that notwithſtanding all your trauells (being my deuice) as gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing indulgences and promiſing heauen to traitrous ſubiects for the diſpatching of their naturall but our aduerſe Princes, or the dailie excommunications thundred againſt the ſaid Princes, we canneither by the curſing of the one, or the bleſsing of the other ſo preuaile, but that the diſciples of <hi>Luther, Caluine, Beza,</hi> and ſuch like back-ſliders from our Church of <hi>Belial,</hi> do openlie &amp; hourelie preach and publiſh his Almightineſſe, whoſe name I tremble to rehearſe; attributing to him, and none but him, all power to forgiue ſinne: whereby my kingdome (founded vpon
<pb facs="tcp:7100:3"/>me the chiefe corner ſtone, and laide together by diuers Popes, Cardinals, Abbots, &amp; other Cloiſterers is ſo ſorelie ſhaken, our pardons, pilgrimages, and purgatorie ſo little feared, that as the walls of <hi>Iericho,</hi> ſo fall our principals at this Euangelicall ſound. This therefore is my will, (which may in no wiſe bee delaied) that ſeeing there is yet ſome hope, by reaſon euerie Chriſtian Prince is not fullie diſſwaded from our faction, there be foorth-with a vniforme League of fatall confederacie by ſuch as fauour vs, againſt our foes; eſpeciallie our Arch-enemies, <hi>Elizabeth</hi> Queene of <hi>England,</hi> &amp; <hi>Henrie</hi> King of <hi>Nauarre:</hi> This League proceeding from my ſpirite of malignitie, (as a Daughter wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie no other father) I would haue thee beautefie with ſome hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriticall ſtile of outward holineſſe, and if thou liſt call it the <hi>Holie League.</hi> Touching the Princes thou ſhalt confeder, I need giue ſmall inſtructions: onelie this I charge that thou be ſodain and circumſpect to aſſemble thy Synode, among whom I will as a chiefe Compeere ſit. The Diuell had no ſooner ſaide theſe words, but a Senate of ſacriligious Shauelings were aſſembled, and Sathan himſelfe by the Popes high Chaire proudlie ſeated? (<hi>as appeareth in the Mappe at the letter</hi> A.) Here was it conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, how this League now named Holie, ſhuld alſo proue migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in operation againſt the Princes profeſsing the Goſpell. Firſt it was ordeined, that the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> (being by nature ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and bloodie, yet through riotous exceſſe vtterlie vnable) ſhould haue his neceſsitie ſupplied with Spaniſh &amp; Romiſh ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluitie: prouided that hee fill <hi>France</hi> with inhumane maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres, (<hi>explaned in the letter</hi> B.) thereby to weaken the King of <hi>Nauarre:</hi> to which he was animated by the Popes Meſſenger, who to whet him on powrde treaſure at his feete (<hi>letter</hi> C.) per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading him alſo to ſtir vp ſuch ill affected Engliſh as he might againſt the perſon of their Royal Souereigne. But <hi>Nauarre</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tefied from heauen, armed at all points like a Chriſtian <hi>Cheua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier</hi> defended the Goſpel (<hi>letter</hi> D.) &amp; <hi>England</hi> happie through her <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> ſate crowned with a wreath of peace (making Chriſt her hope) as a Rocke vnmooueable (<hi>letter</hi> E). This fret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Pope; and <hi>Philip</hi> King of <hi>Spaine</hi> made drunke and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued with the ſuperſtitious cup of Romiſh abhomination, was
<pb facs="tcp:7100:3"/>whetted on according to his promiſe in the Holie League, cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion-like to prepare his people, and diſcharge his abundance of Indian earth: in ſatisfaction of which I warrant yee, hee had no ſmall rewards, for his verie Horſe was trapt with Bulls and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons (<hi>letter</hi> F.) <hi>Allen</hi> alſo that caitiffe Cardinall, and Engliſh Arch-traitor, from his Cannon of corrupt conceipt diſchargeth two ſeditious Libels againſt his Souereign: to which the Engliſh Friers and Seminarie Prieſts giue fire (<hi>letter</hi> G). Now to make this League an able Bodie, to beare downe the aduerſaries of Antichriſt both by land and ſea, her head was beautified with a horned Moone (<hi>letter</hi> H) of huge and mightie ſhippes, readie to ioyne with the bloodie <hi>Guiſe,</hi> and alſo to vnite them to the Prince of <hi>Parma,</hi> that in a moment they might ſwallow vp lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle <hi>England,</hi> as the rauenous Crocodile dooth the ſmalleſt fiſh in the ſeauen mouthd Riuer <hi>Nilus.</hi> But God the onelie Patrone of <hi>England</hi> and our <hi>Elizabeth</hi> diſmaied firſt the appointed Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie of the Prince, ſo that like the <hi>Syrians</hi> that beſieged <hi>Samaria</hi> in the daies of <hi>Eliſeus</hi> the Prophet, they fled away vnſought with from ioyning with their fellowes at Sea, and woulde not by the gentle intreaties nor ſeuere threatnings of the Prince their Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall (<hi>letter</hi> I) be anie waie perſwaded to ſet foote aboord the ſmal Skiffes, appointed to tranſport them to their holie or rather vnhallowed mates: their feare ariſing (as it euidentlie appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red) from that Fleete whereof the Lorde <hi>Seymor</hi> was Generall (<hi>letter</hi> K) which with the <hi>Hollanders</hi> was readie to giue them their deſerued welcome. This Fleete and all the reſt of their worthie warre-fellowes ouerſhaddowed with the wings of the Almightie, honorablie vowed to ſell their worthie liues in the defence of this Iland, (his little <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and their natiue Nourſe) animated couragiouſlie euerie man his mate, with reſolution to attempt the ruine of this vnhallowed League: whoſe Moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Cronet was deckt with ſundrie pendants, of painted Saints, (ſufficient guides for ſuperſtitious ſotts full gaudelie adornde with the fineſt golde, rakte out of wretched <hi>Indiaes</hi> Wombe, whoſe ſenſeleſſe bowells the <hi>Spaniards</hi> (ſlaue-like) ceaſeleſllie teare out (<hi>letter</hi> L), onelie to ſatisfie the rauenous appetites of their Wooluiſh Inquiſitours, who ſubmit forthwith at the feete
<pb facs="tcp:7100:4"/>of their Papall God, the trauailes both of Prince &amp; people, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them vaſſals to an vnworthie Prieſt: and applying their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours gained with venter of their liues, &amp; hazard of their ſoules to the ſtrengthning of the forenamed League. But all is vaine: for the breath of the Lords mouth hath dimmed the brightneſſe of her Moone, and ſcattered thoſe proud ſhippes, whoſe maſts ſeemed like Cedars to dare the Sunne, the treacherous Libels of traiterous <hi>Allen,</hi> are with himſelfe helde infamous to the world: The <hi>Guiſe</hi> alſo (one of greateſt helpes) is dead deſerued lie. She being with theſe ſorrowes ſurcharged, and mangled with manie maimes, ſhe languiſheth in a conſumption on her bed (<hi>letter</hi> M.) The Pope (on earth her cheefe Patrone) promiſeth his helpe in what he maie, &amp; feeling her pulſes, aſſureth her there is yet good hope. But the Deuill belike being the better Doctor, and not louing to diſſemble where his daughter was Patient, proteſts af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had caſt her water, there was euident ſigne of death. Thus is this diueliſh League deuiſed by the Diuell, and confirmed by the Pope, weakned and waſted through the Spirite of Truth, &amp; power of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt: To whome let <hi>England</hi> ſing ſo all her victories; <hi>Not vnto vs ô Lord, not vnto vs, but vnto thy Name be praiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:7100:4"/>
               <head>The Birth, purpoſe, and mortal wound <hi>of the Romiſh Holie League.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>IN ſilent night, when each thing takes it reſt,</l>
                  <l>Yet wakes the Deuill, who neuer ſhuts his eyes:</l>
                  <l>In darkſome night he leaues his lothſome neſt</l>
                  <l>All in a rage, and towards <hi>Rome</hi> he flyes.</l>
                  <l>Where when to Pallace of the <hi>Pope</hi> he came,</l>
                  <l>He enters in, and thus his tale doth frame.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Draw néere my ſonne, and liſten to thy Sire,</l>
                  <l>The world waxeth old and may not long endure,</l>
                  <l>The time drawes on apace, it muſt conſume with fire:</l>
                  <l>Then ends thy kingdome too, which ſtandeth nothing ſure;</l>
                  <l>Becauſe the Goſpell ſpreads it ſelfe apace;</l>
                  <l>While thou and thine, runne headlong to diſgrace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A Councell call of all thy Prelates great:</l>
                  <l>Cardnalls, Friers, and Shauelings of each ſort:</l>
                  <l>And I with thee will ſit vpon thy ſtately Seate,</l>
                  <l>And for thy ruin'd ſtate, erect a mightie fort,</l>
                  <l>And build the ſame with Princes of this land,</l>
                  <l>With other Kings faſt bound in follies band.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Which band, though it be bound, by thee and me my ſonne,</l>
                  <l>Yet muſt it be adorn'd, with title of deuotion;</l>
                  <l>And call it <hi>Holie League,</hi> or els we are vndone,</l>
                  <l>And thou wilt tumble downe from all thy high promotion;</l>
                  <l>And he the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> King which <hi>Phillip</hi> hath to name,</l>
                  <l>Muſt be the chiefeſt of this <hi>League,</hi> and maiſter of the game.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He hath great ſtore of gold, and will not ſpare for coſt:</l>
                  <l>He can ſupplie the <hi>Guizes</hi> want, which now is farre in debt,</l>
                  <l>By ryot and exceſſe, his coyne is ſpent and loſt:</l>
                  <l>And what will he not do, if that it be to get?</l>
                  <l>I tell thee héere my ſonne, thou haſt not ſuch a boy,</l>
                  <l>From Eaſt to Weſt, or any where within thy princely ſway.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:7100:5"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>A fayre religious Cloake, do ſpread vpon his backe,</l>
                  <l>To couer his ambition, his cruell bloodie mind:</l>
                  <l>But Piſtolets of <hi>Spayne,</hi> and Coyne he muſt not lacke</l>
                  <l>To execute thy tyrannie, whereto he is aſſignd,</l>
                  <l>Againſt both Chriſt &amp; Chriſtians that do profeſſe his word:</l>
                  <l>Yet ſay he ſheddeth blood, with noble <hi>Gedeons</hi> ſword.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And I will rule his heart, for there I haue my ſeate;</l>
                  <l>Thy Butcher he ſhal be, and humaine fleſh ſhall ſell:</l>
                  <l>No age his hand ſhall ſpare from ſmalleſt to the great,</l>
                  <l>His minde I will ſo vexe with furies out of Hell:</l>
                  <l>But chiefly he ſhall ayme at the good <hi>Nauarre</hi> King,</l>
                  <l>He is the marke, ſhoot right at him, for thats the only thing.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Giue him no leaue, nor leiſure, for to muſe</l>
                  <l>Upon the ſacred word of his eternall God:</l>
                  <l>But ſtill do him purſue, as other <hi>Popes</hi> did vſe,</l>
                  <l>Being yet in mothers wombe, with their afflicting rod:</l>
                  <l>And euer ſince his birth he hath béen chaſed ſtill:</l>
                  <l>And yet vnto our woe, we cannot haue our will.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He muſt be made away, becauſe he is the heire,</l>
                  <l>And next vnto the Crowne of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> by orderly diſcent:</l>
                  <l>Tis he, tis he, that puts vs all in feare,</l>
                  <l>And he muſt downe, or els you will be ſhent.</l>
                  <l>He cares not for thy Curſe, our <hi>Guyze</hi> muſt do the deede,</l>
                  <l>Thy Bulls nor yet thy Charmes, can neuer make him bléede.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And yet there is a greater foe, and ſhe of greater might;</l>
                  <l>Gainſt whom our deareſt <hi>Guize,</hi> nor ſcarſely <hi>Spayne</hi> I wéene</l>
                  <l>May well preuaile, to put her from her right;</l>
                  <l>She rules braue <hi>Britaine</hi> Iſle, I meane the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Quéene;</l>
                  <l>Gainſt her my ſonne, this <hi>League</hi> muſt ioyne in one,</l>
                  <l>For all too weake our <hi>Spayne</hi> will be alone.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Her Father firſt did wound thee to the hart,</l>
                  <l>Her brother next thy wound did ſtill renewe:</l>
                  <l>But ſiſter yet did ſalue againe thy ſmart,</l>
                  <l>And heald thy wound as all the world did viewe:</l>
                  <l>Till ſhe came in that ouerthrewe thy Crowne,</l>
                  <l>And in her Land by force doth keepe thee downe.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:7100:5"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yea many other Foes, both Kings and Dukes of fame.</l>
                  <l>I knowe we haue, but firſt theſe two muſt downe.</l>
                  <l>Bend all thy force againſt that ſtately Dame;</l>
                  <l>And then the reſt will ſhrinke, if thou but frowne.</l>
                  <l>This Sathan ſayd, wherewith away he vades,</l>
                  <l>He leaues the earth, and flyes to darkſome ſhades.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This gueſt thus gone, they all allowe his tale,</l>
                  <l>And ſtraight proceede to practiſe his pretence:</l>
                  <l>Wherein they had ſuch lucke, there blewe ſo braue a gale,</l>
                  <l>They got their whole deſire, and that with ſmall expence:</l>
                  <l>The King, the Peeres, and many Princes ſeales,</l>
                  <l>Gainſt Heauen, gainſt Chriſt, &amp; Chriſtian Common weales.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And <hi>Phillip</hi> now beſtirres his aged limmes,</l>
                  <l>He beates his braines, he tyres his wearie wit,</l>
                  <l>He ſends for Gold, and homeward faſt it ſwimmes,</l>
                  <l>And ſayth, herewith the marke I meane to hit</l>
                  <l>Whereat ſo long I aymed haue in vayne,</l>
                  <l>To ioyne that famous Land vnto the Crowne of <hi>Spayne.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And Antichriſt doth whippe his poſting haſt with ſpeede:</l>
                  <l>And Cardnall <hi>Allen</hi> he muſt play the gunner ſtout,</l>
                  <l>And ſhoot abroad great bragges, without reſpect or heed,</l>
                  <l>As Champion chiefe amongſt this ruffling rout;</l>
                  <l>So blazing foorth his ſhame, as one deuoyd of grace,</l>
                  <l>Gainſt his and our good Prince, her Crowne &amp; royall place.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then hugie Shippes, as earſt were neuer ſeene,</l>
                  <l>Proud <hi>Spayne</hi> prepares for to inuade our Land:</l>
                  <l>And all againſt the moſt renowmedſt Quéene,</l>
                  <l>That euer yet bare Scepter in her hand.</l>
                  <l>Oh Lord what hath thy Handmayd done to theſe,</l>
                  <l>That thus aſſault her Kingdome and her Seas:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But worthely in thy great iudgements iuſt,</l>
                  <l>Of thy good will thou didſt confound their pride,</l>
                  <l>And made them feele the ſmart of their ambicious luſt,</l>
                  <l>Not daring long our royall Shippes abide,</l>
                  <l>But fled away like ſhéepe before the hound,</l>
                  <l>Still héere and there, ſome going to the ground.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:7100:6"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>They felt the force of <hi>Brittiſh</hi> braue young bloodes,</l>
                  <l>Which queld the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> harts, &amp; made them hide their heads:</l>
                  <l>Some crept belowe the Decke and prayed to their Roodes,</l>
                  <l>And other ſome to other Saints, while Friers tooke their beads.</l>
                  <l>Then at the length, when we forſooke the chaſe,</l>
                  <l>Both wind and waue defied them to the face.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But all this while proud <hi>Parma</hi> with his barges,</l>
                  <l>Could nought preuaile to driue his men aboorde,</l>
                  <l>But loſt his toyle, with all his coſtes and charges:</l>
                  <l>Sometime he ſpake them faire, ſtraight threatning w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his ſword;</l>
                  <l>But all in vaine, his Sailers ranne away,</l>
                  <l>And left his Boates to ſet him home his hay.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>They wift full well, that in the narrowe Seas</l>
                  <l>Was nothing got but ſtripes and <hi>Engliſh</hi> blowes;</l>
                  <l>Which they forſooke, as glad to liue at eaſe,</l>
                  <l>And left the Prince quite bored through the noſe.</l>
                  <l>But God (my friends) he tooke away their barts,</l>
                  <l>To make them knowe his power and furie of his darts.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet that which moſt doth ſhewe the arme of God,</l>
                  <l>In all theſe bloodie broyles we loſt not threeſcore men;</l>
                  <l>To them a certaine ſigne of Heauens heauie rod,</l>
                  <l>To vs a ſhewe of loue: let vs be thankfull then,</l>
                  <l>And praiſe that Lord, which is the Lord of hoaſt,</l>
                  <l>That doth defend and ſhield our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Coaſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And makes our Land abound with fleſh and bread,</l>
                  <l>And cloath moſt fine, from colde to gard our backe:</l>
                  <l>With Timber ſtore, good Iron, Tinne and Lead,</l>
                  <l>And many other things, which other Nations lacke:</l>
                  <l>But yet a greater grace, we haue his word in peace,</l>
                  <l>God graunt it may continue, and bring forth more increaſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let <hi>Spanyard</hi> then go delue and digge for hidden gold;</l>
                  <l>Let him go rend rich <hi>Indies</hi> bowels out;</l>
                  <l>Let him go trie his friends, and let his Buls be ſold;</l>
                  <l>Let him raiſe taxes more, and let him caſt about;</l>
                  <l>Let him, let Pope, let Deuill and all the reſt,</l>
                  <l>Do what they can, yea let them do their beſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:7100:6"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let them not ceaſe to boaſt and bragge to come againe;</l>
                  <l>Let them with ſpeede prepare like Forces trebble tolde:</l>
                  <l>Let vs repent, amend; pray for our Princes raigne;</l>
                  <l>Let vs be true in one, let vs together holde:</l>
                  <l>Come Deuill then, come Pope and all the crewe,</l>
                  <l>And as you ſped of late, ſo ſhall you ſpeede a newe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For <hi>England</hi> yet both is, and ſhall be <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſtill:</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Engliſh</hi> Brutes do brauely keepe the ſame:</l>
                  <l>Though baſtard <hi>Britaines</hi> boaſt and bragge their fill,</l>
                  <l>And leaue their Land and ſkorne the <hi>Engliſh</hi> name:</l>
                  <l>They ſkorne not vs, but bring themſelues in ſkorne;</l>
                  <l>By leauing vs, they léeſe themſelues and ſeede vnborne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Our Papiſtes play the Batte, that left the flying foule;</l>
                  <l>Becauſe he thought that Beaſtes more ſtronger were than they:</l>
                  <l>Who dares not now appeare, but with the ſkriching Owle</l>
                  <l>Flyes alwaies in the night, not daring view the day:</l>
                  <l>So do our Papiſtes proud, who ſkorne our little Ile,</l>
                  <l>In flying to the mightie Beaſts, which now haue got y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foile.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>They would be Birds againe, but ſhame doth beate them back:</l>
                  <l>They wiſh themſelues vnborne, or els vntimely birth:</l>
                  <l>Their hope is ouerthrowne, their Beaſtes be gone to wrack:</l>
                  <l>So they bewaile their loſſe, while we ſing praiſe with mirth.</l>
                  <l>We praiſe our God which doth vs ſafely keepe,</l>
                  <l>While they may howle like hounds, &amp; wring their hands and wéepe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And long may you ſo houle, till you repent and chaunge,</l>
                  <l>And turne vnto the Lord, from whom you go aſtray;</l>
                  <l>And yéeld vnto your Realme, from which you runne &amp; raunge:</l>
                  <l>Good ſubiects to your Prince, become while yet you may;</l>
                  <l>Orels be ſure, more plagues will ſtill enſue</l>
                  <l>Upon your loathſome League, and alſo vpon you.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Which League now lieth ſicke, your Doctors doo deſpaire:</l>
                  <l>Your Pope doth ſcratch his head, your Spaniſh ſhips are loſt:</l>
                  <l>Your Cardinalls crie out, your Friers teare their haire:</l>
                  <l>Your combes now are cut, your Clergie ceaſe to boaſt:</l>
                  <l>The <hi>French</hi> king now eſpies wherto your league was hatche</l>
                  <l>And like a King he cutteth ſhort thoſe that him ouer-matcht.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:7100:7"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Becauſe he ſuffered long, you thought that he would beare:</l>
                  <l>Becauſe that he forbore, you thought ye might him lade:</l>
                  <l>Becauſe once you made him flye, ye thought him ſtill to feare:</l>
                  <l>Becauſe he would not be of <hi>Romiſh League</hi> and trade,</l>
                  <l>You thought to cut him off, you thought him to betray;</l>
                  <l>Which beede your <hi>Guize</hi> muſt do, and make the King away.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But <hi>Guize</hi> hath his reward, and in his guiſe is ſlaine</l>
                  <l>The bloodie <hi>Guize</hi> hath bloodie end, moſt iuſtly to his hire,</l>
                  <l>The bloodieſt man that <hi>France</hi> ere bred, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> made of blood a gaine,</l>
                  <l>Lyes now in duſt, who was your hope and toppe of your deſire.</l>
                  <l>Lothe then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                     <hi>League</hi> that leaueth you, &amp; is in falling downe,</l>
                  <l>Gainſt Chriſt it firſt was made, and Heauens thereat frowne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Forſake the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and flye that man of ſinne,</l>
                  <l>Returne to Chriſt his fold, that you with vs may ioy;</l>
                  <l>And pray with vs in heart, yea let vs neuer lin,</l>
                  <l>That God protect his Church, and keepe from all annoy</l>
                  <l>Our thrice renowmed Quéene, our royall Realme and Land,</l>
                  <l>From ſecrete foes at home, and from the <hi>Romiſh</hi> band.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
